[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
this is jeremy jung for software
engineering radio today i'm talking to
and wilson he's the co-founder and cto
of superbase and welcome to software
engineering radio thanks so much great
to be here
when i hear about super bass i always
hear about it in relation to two other
products
the first is postgres which is a open
source relational database
we've got four shows on it that our
audience can check out and second is
firebase which is a back end as a
service product from google cloud that
provides a nosql data store it provides
authentication and authorization
it has a functions as a service
component
so it's really meant to be
a replacement for you needing to have
your own server
create your own backend you can have
that all be done from firebase
i think a good place for us to start
would be
walking us through
what superbase is and how it relates to
those two products
yeah so we brand ourselves as the open
source firebase alternative that came
primarily from the fact that we
ourselves used it as the alternative to
firebase so so my co-founder paul in his
previous startup was using firestore
and as they started to scale they hit
certain limitations technical scaling
limitations
and he'd always been a huge postgres fan
so he swapped it out for postgres
and then just started plugging in the
bits that were missing like the real
time streams and he used the tool called
postgrest with a t for the crud apis and
so
he just built like the open source
firebase alternative on postgres and
that's kind of where the tagline came
from but the main difference obviously
is that it's relational database and not
a nosql database which means that it's
not actually a drop-in replacement but
it does mean that it kind of opens the
door to a lot more functionality
actually which is hopefully an advantage
for us and it's a hosted form of
postgres so you mentioned that firebase
is different it's a nosql people are
putting in their json objects and things
like that
so
when people are working with super bass
is the experience of is it just i'm
connecting to a postgres database i'm
writing sql and in that regard it's kind
of not really similar to firebase at all
is that kind of right
yeah i mean the other important thing to
note is that you
can communicate with superbase directly
from the client which is what people
love about firebase is you just like put
the credentials in the client you write
some security rules and then you just
start sending your data
obviously with superbase you do need to
create your schema because it's
relational but apart from that the
experience of client-side development is
very much the same or very similar the
interface obviously the api is a little
bit different but it's similar in that
regard but i think like i said we are
just a database company actually
and the tagline
just explained
really well kind of the concept of what
it is like a back end as a service it
has the real time streams it has the
auth layer it has the auto generated
apis
so i don't know how long we'll stick
with the tagline i think we'll probably
outgrow it at some point but it does do
a good job of communicating roughly what
the service is
so when we talk about it being similar
to firebase the part that's similar to
firebase is that you could be
a person building at the front end part
of the website
and
you don't need to necessarily have a
back-end application because all of that
could talk to superbase and superbase
can handle the authentication
the real-time notifications all those
sorts of things similar to firebase
where basically you only need to write
the front-end part and then you have to
know how to set up supabase in this case
yeah exactly and some of the other we
love firebase by the way we're not
building an alternative to try and
destroy it it's kind of like we're just
building the sql alternative and we take
a lot of inspiration from it and the
other thing we love is that you can
administer your database from the
browser so you go into firebase and you
have the you can see the object tree and
when you're in development you can edit
some of the documents in real time and
so we took that experience and
effectively built like a spreadsheet
view inside of our dashboard
and also obviously have a sql editor in
there as well and trying to create this
like a similar developer experience
because that's where firebase just
excels is the dx is incredible
and so we take a lot of inspiration from
it in those respects as well
and to make it clear to our listeners as
well when you talk about this interface
that's kind of like a spreadsheet and
things like that i suppose it's similar
to somebody opening up pg admin i
suppose and and going in and editing the
rows but maybe you've got like another
layer on top that just makes it a little
more user friendly a little bit more
like something you would get from
firebase i guess
yeah and we take a lot of inspiration
from pg admin pg admins also open source
so i think we've contributed a few
things in or trying to upstream a few
things into pt admin the other thing
that we took a lot of inspiration from
for the table editor what we call it is
airtable and because airtable is
effectively a relational database that
you can just come in and you know click
to add your columns click to add a new
table
and so we just want to reproduce that
experience but again backed up by a full
postgres
dedicated database so when you're
working with a postgres database
normally you need some kind of layer in
front of it right that the person can't
open up their website and connect
directly to postgres from their browser
and you mentioned
postgrest before i wonder if you could
explain a little bit about what that is
and how it works yeah definitely so yeah
postgresql has been around for a while
it's basically a server that you connect
to your postgres database and it
introspects
your schemas
and generates an api for you based on
you know the table names the column
names and then you can basically then
communicate with your postgres database
via this restful
api so you can do pretty much most of
the filtering operations that you can do
in sql quality filters you can even do
full text search over the api
so it just means that whenever you
obviously add a new table or a new
schema or a new
column the api just updates instantly so
you don't have to worry about writing
that middle layer which was always the
drag right whenever you start a new
project it's like okay i've got my
schema i've got my clients now i have to
do all the
connecting code in the middle which is
kind of no developer should need to
write that layer in 2022.
so this the layer you're referring to
when i think of a traditional
web application i think of having to
write routes controllers and create this
this sort of structure where i know all
the tables in my database but the
controllers i create may not map
one-to-one with those tables
and so you mentioned a little bit about
how postgrest looks at the schema and
starts to build an api automatically and
i wonder we could explain a little bit
about how it does those mappings or if
you're writing those yourself yeah it
basically does them automatically by
default it will you know map every table
every column
when you want to start restricting
things well there's two parts to this
there's one thing which i'm sure we'll
get into which is how is this secure
since you're communicating direct from
the client but the other part is what
you mentioned giving like a reduced view
of a particular bit of data and for that
we just use postgres views so you define
a view which might be you know it might
have joins across a couple of different
tables or it might just be a limited set
of columns on one of your tables
and then you can choose to just expose
that view
so it sounds like when you would
typically create a controller and create
a route instead you create a view within
your postgres database and then
postgrest can
take that view and create an endpoint
for it map it to that
yeah exactly
and postgresql is an open source
project right i wonder if you could talk
a little bit about
sort of what its history was how did you
come to choose it yeah i think paul
probably read about it on hacker news at
some point any time it appears on hacker
news it just gets upvoted to the front
page because it's so awesome and we got
connected to the maintainer steve chavez
at some point i think he just took an
interest in well we took an interest in
postgresql and we kind of got acquainted
and then we found out that you know
steve was open to work and
this kind of like probably shaped a lot
of the way we think about building out
super base as a project and as a company
in that we then decided to employ steve
full time but just to work on postgresql
because it's obviously a huge benefit
for us we're very reliant on it we want
it to succeed because it helps our
business
and then as we started to add the other
components we
decided that we would then always look
for existing tools existing open source
projects that exist before we decided to
build something from scratch so as we're
starting to
try and replicate the
features of firebase we would and auth
is a great example
we did a full audit of what are all the
authorization and authentication open
source tools that are out there and
which one was if any would fit best and
we found and netlified built a library
called go true written and go which did
pretty much exactly what we needed so we
just adopted
that and now obviously we just have a
lot of people on the team contributing
to go through as well
you touched on this a little bit earlier
normally when you connect to a postgres
database
your user has permission to basically
everything i guess by default anyways
and so how does that work when you want
to restrict people's permissions make
sure they only get to see records
they're allowed to see how is that all
configured in postgresql and what's
happening you know behind the scenes
yeah the great thing about postgres is
it's got this concept of row level
security which actually i don't think i
even really looked at until we were
building out this auth feature where the
security rules live in your database as
sql so you do like a create policy query
and you say anytime someone tries to
select or insert or update apply this
policy and then
how it all fits together
is our auth server go true
someone will basically make a request to
sign in or sign up with email and
password and we create that user inside
the database they get issued a uuid
and they get issued a json web token or
jwt
which when they have it on the client
side proves that they are this uuid they
have access to this data then when they
make a request via postgrest they send
the jwt in the authorization header
then postgres
will pull out that jwt check the sub
claim which is the uuid and compare it
to any
rows in the database
according to the policy that you wrote
so the most basic one is you say in
order to access this row it must have a
column uuid and it must match whatever
is in the jwt so we basically push
the authorization down into the database
which actually has you know a lot of
other benefits and that as you write new
clients
you don't need to
have it live you know on an api layer or
on the client it's kind of just
everything is managed from the database
so the uuid you mentioned that
represents the user correct
yeah and then
does that map to a user in post graphs
or is there some other way that you're
mapping those permissions
yeah so when you connect go true which
is the auth server to your postgres
database for the first time
it installs its own schema so you'll
have an auth schema and inside will be
auth.users with a list of the users
it'll have a
oauth.tokens which will store all the
access tokens that it's issued and one
of the columns on the orth.users table
will be uuid then whenever you write
application
specific schemas you can just join and
do a foreign key relation to the
auth.users table so it all gets into
schema design and and hopefully we do a
good job of having some good education
content in the docs as well because one
of the things we struggled with from the
start was how much do we abstract
away from sql away from postgres and how
much do we educate and we actually
landed on the educate side because i
mean once you start learning about
postgres it becomes kind of a superpower
for you as a developer and so we'd much
rather
have people discover us because we're a
firebase alternative front-end devs and
then we help them with things like
schema design learning about row level
security because it ultimately like if
you try and abstract that stuff it gets
kind of crappy and maybe not such a
great experience to make sure i
understand correctly so you have
go true which is a netlify open source
project that go to project creates some
tables in your database that has like
you mentioned the tokens the different
users
somebody makes a request to go through
like here's my
username my password go true gives them
back a jwt
and then from your front end you send
that jwt to
the postgrest endpoint and from that jwt
it's able to know which user you are
and then uses postgres's built-in
row level security to figure out which
rows you're allowed to bring back did i
get that right that is pretty much
exactly how it works and it's impressive
that you garnered that without looking
at a single diagram
[Music]
but yeah and obviously we provide a
client library super base gis
which actually does a lot of this work
for you so you don't need to manually
attach the jwt in a header
if you've authenticated with superbase
js then every request sent to postgrest
after that point the header will just be
attached automatically and you'll be in
a session as that user and the users
that we're talking about when we talk
about
postgres's row level security
are those actual users in postgres like
if i was to
log in with p sql i could actually log
in with those users
they're not you could potentially
structure it that way but it would be
more advanced it's basically just users
in the author users table the way it's
currently done i see and postgres has
that row level security is able to work
with that table you don't need to have
actual postgres users
exactly and it's basically
your incomplete i mean you can write
extremely complex auth policies you can
say
you know only give access to this
particular admin group on a thursday
afternoon between six and eight pm
you can get really yeah really as fancy
as you want is that all written in sql
or are there other languages they allow
you to use
yeah the default is plain sql within
postgres itself you can use
i think you can use like there's a
python extension
there's a javascript extension which is
a i think it's a subset of javascript i
mean this is the thing with postgres
it's super extensible and people have
probably got all kinds of interpreters
so you yeah you can use whatever you
want but the
typical user will just use sql
interesting and that applies to
logic in general i suppose where
if you were writing a rails application
you might write ruby if you're writing a
note application you write javascript
but you're saying in a lot of cases with
postgres you're actually able to do what
you want to do whether that's
serialization or mapping objects do that
all through sql yeah exactly exactly and
then obviously like there's a lot of
awesome other stuff that postgres has
like this postgis which if you're doing
geo if you've got like a geo application
it'll load it up with geo types for you
which you can just use if you're doing
uh like encryption and decryption we
just added pg lib sodium which is a new
and awesome cryptography extension and
so you can use all of these these all
add like functions like sql functions
which you can kind of use in any parts
of the logic or in the row level
policies yeah and something i thought
was a little unique about postgrest is
that i believe it's written in haskell
is that right
yeah exactly and it makes it fairly
inaccessible to me
as a result but the good thing is it's
got a thriving community of its own and
you know and there's people who
contribute probably because it's written
in haskell and it's just a really
awesome project and it's an excuse to
contribute to it but yeah i think i did
probably the intro course like many
people and beyond that it's just yeah
kind of inaccessible to me
yeah i suppose that's the trade-off
right is you have a really passionate
community about like people who really
want to use haskell and then you've got
the i guess the group like yourselves
that looks at it and goes oh i don't
know about this
i would love to have the time to invest
in it not practical right now
you talked a little bit about the go
true project from netlify i think i saw
in one of your blog posts that you
actually forked it can you sort of
explain the reasoning behind doing that
yeah initially it was because we
trying to move extremely fast so we did
y combinator in 2020 and when you do y
combinator you get like a a group
partner they call it one of the partners
from yc and they
add a huge amount of external pressure
to move very quickly and our biggest
feature that we were working on in that
period was off and we just kept getting
the question of like when are you gonna
ship off you know and every single week
we'd be like we're working on it we're
working on it and one of the ways we
could do it was we just had to iterate
extremely quickly and we didn't really
have the time to upstream things
correctly and actually like the way
we use it in our stack is slightly
differently they connected to my sql we
connected to postgres so we had to make
some structural changes to do that and
the dream would be now that we spend
some time
up streaming a lot of the changes and
hopefully we do get around to that but
the yeah the pace at which we've had to
move over the last year and a half has
been kind of scary and that's the main
reason but you know hopefully now
we're a little bit more established we
can
hire some more people to just focus on
go through and and bringing the two
forks back together yeah it's just a
matter of
like you said the speed i suppose
because the postgrest you chose to
continue working off of the existing
open source project right
yeah exactly exactly and i think the
other thing is it's not a major part of
netlify's business as i understand it i
think if it was and if both companies
had more resource behind it it would
make sense to
obviously focus on the single code
baseball i think both companies don't
contribute as much resource as we would
like to
but for me it's one of my favorite parts
of the stack to work on because it's
written in go
and i kind of enjoy how
it all fits together so yeah i like to
dive in there
what about go or what about how it's
structured do you particularly enjoy
about that part of the project
so i actually learned to go through go
true and i have like a python and c plus
plus backgrounds and i
hate the fact that i don't get to use
python and c plus plus really in my
day-to-day job it's obviously a lot of
typescript and then when we inherited
this code base it was kind of as i was
picking it up it just reminded me a lot
of the things i loved about python and c
plus and
and the tooling around it as well i just
found to be exceptional
so you know you just do like a small
amount of config and it makes it very
difficult to write bad code if that
makes sense so the compiler will just
boot you back if you try and do
something silly which isn't necessarily
the case with javascript i think
typescript's a little bit better now but
it just reminded me a lot of my python
and cds yeah i'm not too familiar with
go but my understanding is that there's
a formatter that's a part of the
language so there's kind of consistency
there and then the language itself tries
to get people to build things in the
same way or maybe have simpler ways of
building things i don't know maybe
that's part of the appeal yeah exactly
and the package manager as well
is great it just does a lot of the
importing automatically and make sure
like all the the declarations at the top
are formatted correct and are definitely
there so yeah just all of that tool
chain is just really easy to pick up
yeah and i think compiled languages as
well when you have the static type
checking
by the compiler you know not having
things blow up and run times it's just
such a big relief at least for me in a
lot of cases i just love the dopamine
hit of when
you compile something and it actually
compiles this
yeah i lose that with working with
javascript
for sure one of the topics you mentioned
earlier was how
super bass provides real-time database
updates which is something that as far
as i know is not
natively a part of postgres so i wonder
if you could explain a little bit about
how that works and how that came about
yeah so postgres when you add
replication databases the way it does it
is it writes everything to this thing
called the writer headlog which is
basically all the changes that are going
to be applied to the database and when
you connect like a replication database
it basically streams that log across and
that's how the replica knows what
changes to add so we wrote a server
which basically pretends to be a
postgres replica
receives the writer headlog encodes it
into json and then you can subscribe to
that server over websockets and so
you can choose
whether to subscribe to changes on a
particular
schema or a particular table or
particular columns
and even do equality matches on rows and
things like this and then we recently
added the row level security policies to
the real time stream as well so that was
something that took us a while to
because it was
probably one of the largest technical
challenges we'd faced but now that it's
in the real time
stream is fully secure and you can apply
the same policies that you apply over
the crude api as well so for that part
did you have to look into the internals
of postgres and how it did its row level
security and try to duplicate that in
your own code yeah pretty much i mean
it's fairly complex and
there's a guy on our team who
well for him it didn't seem as complex
let's say
but yeah that's pretty much it it's just
a lot of it's effectively a sequel a
postgres extension itself which
interprets those policies and applies
them to the writer headlock and this
piece that you wrote that's listening to
the write ahead log what was it written
in and how did you choose that language
or that stack yeah that's written in the
elixir framework which is based on
airline
very
horizontally scalable so any
applications that you write in elixir
can kind of just scale horizontally the
message passing can
you know go into the billions and it's
no problem
so it just seemed like a sensible choice
for this type of application where you
don't know
how large the while is going to be so it
could just be like a few changes per
second it could be a million changes per
second then you need to be able to scale
out and i think paul who's my co-founder
originally he wrote the first version of
it and i think he wrote it as
an excuse to lay on elixir which is
probably how postgresql ended up being
haskell i imagine but uh
but it's meant that the elixir community
is still like relatively small but it's
a group of like very passionate and very
highly skilled developers so when we
hire from that pool everyone who comes
on board is just like just really good
and really enjoys working with elixir so
it's been a good source for hires as
well just using those tools
software engineers you've been there
something's broken and you and your
whole team are scrambling to find and
fix it that's why you need new relic it
combines 16 different monitoring
products so you can see across your
entire software stack it pinpoints
issues down to the line of code so you
know exactly why the problem happened
and can fix it quick
get access to the whole new relic
platform and 100 gigs of data free right
now at newrelic.com
s e radio
that's newrelic.com
with a feature like this i'm assuming
it's where somebody goes to their
website they make a websocket connection
to your application and they receive the
updates that way
have you seen
how far you're able to push that in
terms of connections in terms of
throughput things like that yeah i don't
actually have the numbers at hand but we
have yeah we have a team focused on
obviously maximizing that but yeah don't
have those numbers right now
one of the last things you've got on
your website is a storage product
and i believe it's written in typescript
so i was curious we've got
postgrest which is in haskell we've got
go true and go
we've got the real-time database part in
elixir and so with storage how did we
finally get to typescript
well the policy we kind of landed on
was best tool for the job again the good
thing about being open source is
when not resource constrained by the
number of people who are in our team
it's by the number of people who are in
the community and and willing to
contribute and so
for that
i think one of the guys just went
through a few different options like we
could have went with go just to keep it
in line with a couple of the other apis
but we just decided you know a lot of
people
well everyone in the team
like typescript is kind of just a given
and again it was
kind of down to speed like what's the
fastest we can get this up and running
and i think if we use typescript it was
the best solution there but we just
always go with whatever is best we don't
worry too much about the resources we
have because the open source community
has just been
so great in helping us build super bass
and building super bass is like building
like five companies at the same time
actually because each of these
vertical stacks could be its own startup
like the earth stack and the storage
layer and all of this stuff and you know
each does have its own dedicated team so
yeah so we're not too worried about the
variation in languages and the storage
layer is this basically a wrap or a
round s3 or like what is that product
doing
yeah exactly it's wrapped around s3 it
would also work with all of the s3
compatible storage systems there's a few
backblaze and a few others
so if you wanted to self-host and use
one of those alternatives you could we
just have everything in our own s3
bucket inside of aws and then the other
awesome thing about the storage system
is that because we store the metadata
inside of postgres so basically the
object tree of what buckets and folders
and files are there you can write your
row level policies against the object
tree so you can say this user should
only access this folder and its children
which was kind of kind of an accident we
just landed on that but it's one of my
favorite things now about writing
applications and super bases is the role
of policies kind of work everywhere yeah
it's interesting it sounds like
everything whether it's the storage or
the authentication it's all
comes back to postgres right at all it's
using the row level security it's using
everything that you put into the tables
there and everything's just kind of
digging into that to get what it needs
yeah and that's why i say we are a
database company we are a postgres
company we're all in on postgres we got
asked in the early days oh well would
you also make it my sequel compatible or
compatible with something else and but
the amount of features postgres has
if we just like continue to leverage
them then it just makes the stack way
more powerful than if we tried to go
thin across multiple different databases
and so that kind of brings me to you
mentioned how your postgres companies so
when somebody signs up for super bass
they create their first instance
what's happening behind the scenes are
you creating a postgres instance for
them in a container for example how do
you size it that sort of thing yeah so
it's basically just ec2 under the hood
for us we have plans eventually to be
multi-cloud but again going down to
speed of execution the fastest way was
to just spin up a dedicated instance a
dedicated postgres instance per user on
ec2 we do also
package all of the apis together in a
second ec2 instance
but we're starting to
break those out into clustered services
so for example
you know not every user will use the
storage api so it doesn't make sense to
run it for every user regardless so
we've made that multi-tenant the
application code and now we just run a
huge global cluster which people connect
through to access the s3 bucket
basically and we have plans to do that
for the other services as well so right
now it's you get two ec2 instances but
over time it'll be just the postgres
instance and we wanted to give everyone
a dedicated instance because
there's nothing worse than
sharing database resource with other
users
especially when you don't know how
heavily they're going to use it whether
they're going to be bursty
so i think one of the things we just
said from the start is everyone gets a
postgres instance and you get
access to it as well you can you know
use your postgres connection string to
log in from the command line and kind of
do whatever you want it's yours so did i
get it right that
when i sign up i create a superbase
account
you're actually creating an ec2 instance
for me specifically so it's like every
customer gets their own isolated it's
their own cpu their own ram that sort of
thing
yeah exactly exactly and the way the
we've set up the monitoring as well is
that we can expose basically all of that
to you in the dashboard as well so you
have some control over like the resource
you want to use if you wanna
a more powerful instance we can do that
a lot of that stuff is automated so if
someone scales beyond the allocated disk
size the disk will automatically scale
up by 50 each time and we're working on
automating a bunch of these other things
as well
so is it where
when you first create the account you
might create for example a micro
instance and then you have internal
monitoring tools that see
oh the cpu is getting hit pretty hard so
we need to migrate this person to a
bigger instance that kind of thing yeah
pretty much exactly and is that
something that the user would even see
or is it the case of where you send them
an email and go like hey we notice
you're hitting the limits here here's
what's gonna happen
yeah in most cases it's handled
automatically
there are people who come in
and from day one they say here's my
requirements i'm gonna have this much
traffic i'm going to have you know 100
000 users
hitting this every hour and in those
cases we will over provision from the
start
but if it's just the self-service case
then it will be start on you know a
smaller instance and upgrade over time
and
this is one of our biggest challenges
over the next five years is we want to
move
to a more scalable postgres so cloud
native postgres but the cool thing about
this is there's a lot of different
companies and individuals working on
this and up streaming it into postgres
itself so for us we don't need to
and we would never want to fork postgres
and try and separate the storage and the
the compute but more we're gonna fund
people who are already working on this
so that it gets upstreamed into postgres
itself and it's more cloud native yeah
so i think the
like we talked a little bit about how
firebase was the original inspiration
and
when you work with firebase you don't
think about an instance at all right you
just put data in you get data out and it
sounds like in this case you're kind of
working from the standpoint of we're
going to give you this single postgres
instance as you hit the limits we'll
give you a bigger one
but at some point you will hit a limit
of where just that one instance is not
enough and i wonder if you have any
plans
for that or if you're doing anything
currently to handle that yeah so the
medium goal
is to
do replication like horizontal scaling
we do that for some users already but we
manually set that up
we do want to bring that to the
self-serve and model as well where you
can just choose from the start i want
you know wrap-up is in these zones and
in these different data centers but then
like i said the long-term goal is that
it's not based on
horizontally scaling a number of
instances it's just that postgres itself
can scale out and i think honestly the
rate at which the postgres community is
working i think we'll be there in two
years
and if we can contribute resource
towards that goal i think yeah like we'd
love to do that but for now we're
working on this intermediate solution of
what people already do with postgres
which is you know have your replicas to
make it highly available
and with that i suppose
at least in the short term the goal is
that
your monitoring software and your team
is handling the
scaling up the instance or creating the
read replicas so to the user it for the
most part feels like a managed service
and then yeah the next step would be to
get something more similar to
maybe amazon's aurora i suppose where it
just kind of you pay per use i suppose
yeah exactly exactly aurora was kind of
the goal from the start it's just a
shame that it's proprietary obviously i
think the world would be a better place
if aurora was open source
yeah it sounds like you said there's
people in the open source community that
are trying to get there just it'll take
time to all this about
making it feel
seamless making it feel like a
server-less experience even though
internally it really isn't i'm guessing
you must have
a fair amount of monitoring or ways that
you're making these decisions i wonder
if you can talk a little bit about you
know what are the metrics you're looking
at and what are the applications you
have to help you make these decisions
yeah definitely so we started with
prometheus which is a
metrics gathering tool and then we moved
to victoria metrics which was just
easier for us to scale out i think soon
we'll be
managing like a hundred thousand
postgres databases will have been
deployed on super base so definitely
some scale so this kind of tooling needs
to scale to that as well and then we
have agents
kind of everywhere on each application
on the database itself and we listen for
things like the cpu and the ram
and the network io
we also
poll
postgres itself there's a extension
called pg stat statements which will
give us information about what are the
intensive queries that are running on
that box so we just collect as much of
this as possible which we then obviously
use internally we set alerts to know
when we need to upgrade in a certain
direction but we also have an endpoint
where the dashboard subscribes to these
metrics as well so the user themselves
can see a lot of this information and i
think at the moment we do a lot of the
ram the cpu
that kind of stuff but we're working on
adding just more and more of these
observability metrics so people can know
because it also helps with let's say you
might be lacking an index on a
particular table and not know about it
and so if we can expose that to you and
give you alerts about that kind of thing
then it obviously helps with the
developer experience as well yeah and
that brings me to something that i hear
from platform as a service companies
where
if a user has a problem whether that's a
crash or a performance problem sometimes
it can be difficult to distinguish
between is it a problem in their
application or is this a problem in
supabase or you know and i wonder how
your support team kind of approaches
that yeah no it's a great question and
it's definitely something we deal with
every day i think because of where we're
at as a company we've always
seen like we actually have a huge
advantage in that we can provide
really good support so anytime an
engineer joins super base we tell them
your primary job is actually frontline
support
everything you do
afterwards is secondary and so everyone
does a four hour shift per week of
working directly with the customers to
help determine this kind of thing and
where we are at the moment is we are
happy to dive in and help people with
their application code because it helps
our engineers learn about how it's being
used and where the pitfalls are where we
need better documentation where we need
education so that is all part
of the product at the moment actually
and like i said because we're not a 10
000 person company it's an advantage
that we have that we can deliver that
level of support at the moment what are
some of the most common
things you see happening like is it i
would expect you mentioned indexing
problems but i'm wondering if there's
any specific things that just come up
again and again i think like the most
common is people not batching
their requests so they'll write an
application which you know needs to pull
10 000
rows
and they send 10 000 requests
that's a typical one for people just
getting started maybe and then i think
the other thing we faced in the early
days was people storing blobs in the
database which we obviously solved that
problem by introducing file storage but
people would be trying to store
you know
50 megabytes 100 megabyte files in
postgres itself and then asking why the
performance was so bad
so i think we've mitigated that one by
introducing the blob storage and you
mentioned you have
over a hundred thousand instances
running
i imagine there have to be
cases where an incident occurs where
something doesn't go quite right and i
wonder if you could give an example of
one and how it was resolved
yeah it's a good question we've improved
the systems since then but there was a
period where
our real-time server wasn't able to
handle
really large write ahead logs so it was
a period where people were just
making tons and tons of requests and
updates to postgres and the real-time
subscriptions were failing
but like i said we have some really
great elixir devs on the team so they
were able to jump on that fairly quickly
and now you know the application is way
more scalable as a result and that's
just kind of how the support model works
is you you have a period where
everything is breaking and then you just
you know tackle these things one by one
yeah i think anybody
at a an early startup is going to run
into that right you put it out there and
then you find out what's broken you fix
it and you just get better and better as
it goes along yeah and the funny thing
was this model of deploying ec2
instances
we had that in like the first week of
starting super bass just me and paul
and it was never intended to be the
final solution we just kind of did it
quickly to get something up and running
for our first handful of users
but it scaled surprisingly well
and actually the things that broke as we
started to get a lot of traffic and a
lot of attention were just silly things
like
we give everyone their own sub domain
when they start a new project so you'll
have project
ref.superbase.in or dot co and the
things that were breaking were like you
know we ran out of sub domains with our
dns provider and those things always
happen in periods of like intense
traffic so we were on the front page of
hack news or we had a techcrunch article
and then you discover that you've ran
out of sub domains and the last thousand
people couldn't deploy their projects so
that's always a fun challenge because
you are then dependent on the external
provider as well and their support
systems
so yeah i think we did
a surprisingly good job of putting in
good infrastructure from the start but
yeah all of these crazy things just
break when obviously when you get a lot
of traffic yeah i find it interesting
that you mentioned how you started with
creating the ec2 instances it turned out
that just worked i wonder if you could
walk me through a little bit about
how it worked in the beginning like was
it the two of you going in and creating
instances as people signed up and then
how it went from there to where it is
today
yeah so there's a good story about our
first user actually
so me and paul used to contract for a
company in singapore which was a an nft
company and so we knew the lead
developer very well and we also still
had the postgres credentials on our own
machines and so what we did was we set
up the and the other funny thing is when
we first started we didn't intend to
host the database we thought we were
just going to host the applications that
would connect to your existing postgres
instance and so what we did was we
hooked up the applications to the
postgres instance of this startup that
we knew very well and then we took the
bus to their office and we sat with the
lead developer and we said look we've
already set this thing up for you
what do you think
and
you know when you think like ah we've
got the best thing ever but it's not
until you put it in front of someone and
you see them
you know
contemplating it and you're like oh
maybe it's not so good maybe we don't
have anything and we had that moment of
panic of like oh maybe we just don't
maybe this isn't great and then what
happened was he didn't like use us he
didn't become a super based user he
asked to join the team
nice nice so that was a good moment
where we thought okay maybe we have got
something maybe this isn't terrible so
he became our first employee and so that
case was you know the very beginning you
set everything up from scratch now that
you have people signing up and you have
you know i don't know how many sign ups
you get a day did you write custom
infrastructure or applications to do the
provisioning or is there an open source
project that you're using to handle that
yeah it's actually mostly custom you
know aws does a lot of the heavy lifting
for you they just provide you with a
bunch of api endpoints so a lot of that
is just written in typescript
fairly straightforward and like i said
you never intended to be the thing that
lasts
two years into the business but it's
just scaled surprisingly well and i'm
sure at some point we'll swap it out for
some i don't know orchestration tooling
like palumi or something like this but
actually what we've got just works
really well because we're so into
postgres our queuing system is a
postgres extension called pg boss and
then we have a fleet of workers which
are we manage on ecs so it's just a
bunch of vms basically which just
subscribe to the cue which lives inside
the database and just performs all the
whether it be a project creation
deletion modification a whole suite of
these things yeah very cool so even your
provisioning is based on postgres
yeah exactly exactly
i guess in that case i think did you say
you're using the right ahead log there
too in order to get notifications or
we do use real time this is the fun
thing about building superfaces we use
super bass to build super bass a lot of
the features start with things that we
build for ourselves so the observability
features we have a huge logging division
so we were very early users of a tool
called log flair which is also written
elixir it's basically a log sync backed
up by bigquery and we loved it so much
and we became like super log flare power
users that it was kind of we decided to
eventually acquire the company and now
we can just offer log flair to all of
our customers as well as part of using
superbase so you can query your logs get
really good business intelligence on
what your users consuming from your
database the lock flare you're
mentioning though you said that that's a
log sync and that that's actually not
going to postgres right that's going to
a different type of store yeah that is
going to bigquery actually oh big query
okay
yeah and maybe eventually and this is
the cool thing about watching the
postgres
progression is it's bringing like
transactional and analytical databases
together so it's traditionally been a
great transactional database
but if you look at a lot of the changes
that have been made in recent versions
it's becoming closer and closer to
an analytical database so maybe at some
point we'll use it but yeah but bigquery
works just great yeah it's interesting
to see like i know that we've had
episodes on different extensions to
postgres where i believe they change out
how the storage works so there's yeah
it's really interesting how it's this
one database but it seems like it can
take so many different forms
it's just so extensible and that's why
we're so bullish on it because okay
maybe it wasn't always the best database
but now it seems like it is becoming the
best database and the rate at which it's
moving is like where is it going to be
in five years and we're just yeah we're
just very bullish on on postgres as you
can tell from the amount of mentions
it's had in this episode
yeah we'll have to count how many times
it's been said i'm sure it's
sure it's up there is there anything
else we missed or think you should have
mentioned
no some of the things we're excited
about are cloud functions
so it's the thing we just get asked for
the most anytime we post anything on
twitter
you're guaranteed to get a reply which
is like when functions and we're very
pleased to say that it's almost there so
that will hopefully be a really good
developer experience where also
we launched like a graphql postgres
extension
where the resolver lives inside of
postgres and
that's still in early alpha but i think
i'm quite excited for when we can start
offering that on the hosted platform as
well people will have that option to use
graphql instead of or as well as the
restful api the common thread here is
that postgres you're able to take it
really really far right in terms of
scale up eventually you'll have the read
replicas hopefully you'll have
some kind of i don't know what you would
call aurora but it's almost like
self-provisioning maybe not sure what
how you describe it but i wonder as a
company like we talked about bigquery
right i wonder if there's any use cases
that you've come across either from
customers or in your own work where
you're like i just can't get it to fit
into postgres
i think like
not very often but sometimes we will
respond to
support requests and recommend that
people use firebase so if they
really
do have like large amounts of
unstructured data which is you know
document storage is kind of perfect for
then we'll just say you know maybe you
should just use firebase
so we definitely come across things like
that and like i said we love firebase so
we're definitely not trying to destroy
it as a tool i think it has its use
cases where it's an incredible tool yeah
and provides a lot of inspiration for
what we're building as well
all right well i think that's a good
place to wrap it up but where can people
hear more about you hear more about
super bass
yeah so super bass is at superbase.com
i'm on twitter at ant wilson superbasses
on twitter at superbase just hit us up
we're quite active on there and then
definitely check out the repos
github.com
superbase there's lots of great stuff to
dig into as we discussed there's a lot
of different languages so kind of
whatever you're into you'll probably
find something where you can contribute
yeah and we sort of touched on this but
i think
everything we've talked about with the
exception of the provisioning part and
the monitoring part is all open source
is that correct
yeah and hopefully everything we
build moving forward including functions
and graphql will continue to be open
source and i suppose the one thing i did
mean to touch on is what is the license
for all the components you're using that
are open source
it's mostly apache 2 or mit
and then obviously postgres has its own
postgres license so as long as it's one
of those then we're not too precious as
i said we inherit a fair amount of
projects or we contribute to an adopt
project so
as long as it's just very permissive
then we don't care too much
as far as the projects that your team
has worked on i've noticed that over the
years we've seen a lot of companies move
to things like the business source
license or there's there's all these
different licenses that are not quite so
permissive and i wonder like what your
thoughts are
on that for the future of your company
and why you think that you'll be able to
stay permissive yeah i really really
really hope that we can stay permissive
forever it's a philosophical thing for
us you know when we we started the
business it's we're just very as
individuals into the idea of open source
and if aws come along at some point and
offer
hosted super bass on aws then it'll be a
signal that we're doing something right
and at that point we just i think we
just need to be
the best team to continue to move super
bass forward and if we are that and i
think we will be there then hopefully we
will never have to tackle this licensing
issue
all right well i wish you luck
thanks thanks for having me this has
been jeremy jung for software
engineering radio thanks for listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening